This is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society and by its software magazine online at computer.org/software
[music]
for software engineering radio. This is Robert Blumen.
Today I am joined by G Mullet.
G is a senior principal product security engineer and technical adviser for product security at Red Hat.
He's worked in security at Red Hat since 2013.
His current focus is on the intersection of AI security safety and trust.
G is the primary author of Red Hat Security Guiding Principles.
G, welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you. It's good to be here. I'm a little bit nervous. This is the first time I've done something like this.
Yes, we have many guests with no podcast experience and they all work out great.
So, I'm no worried at all.
G, today you and I will be talking about AI supply chain security.
Software supply chain security is a topic that we have covered many times on the podcast,
most recently episode 712 on SIG store, but we have not covered AI supply chain security.
Let's start out with some basic definitions.
We're talking about AI in the supply chain. What are we talking about?
Okay, so I think it's important to quickly note what we mean by the software supply chain to start with, which is the supply chain analogies referring to when we're building things, construction and stuff.
And it's what each part of that contributes to the next part.
And in software, we have a similar model, although in reality, it's more of a directional graph than it is a chain.
But that's a whole another topic that I'm sure you've covered already.
The key difference, I think, with the AI software supply chain is that we're no longer producing source code to binary deterministic artifacts.
We're not shipping something that's a translation of instructions that when you run it, it does basically it should do what you've written down.
I know there's nuance and things that can creep in.
But in AI, it becomes entirely non-deterministic like the relationship between the input and the output. It's not binary at all.
It's a probabilistic model.
It turns intent into content.
And that content can be lots of different things.
In generative AI, the most popular things that we see are LLMs, which is what unless you've been living under a rock for the last 2 years, you've probably heard about it just about everywhere.
Those are large language models which they're designed to predict the next word or the next token actually, but we'll just say word for simplicity in a string of text.
So you give it one part of text and it tells you what the next word is most likely to be and you keep going until you have entire large amounts of text.
And we've got really good at turning that into things that are actually useful.
There's other types of AI obviously as well machine learning other types of generative AI but this is what most people are talking about when they talk about AI now are talking about large language models.
Somewhere a few years ago, I think between the GP2 to GPT3 time frame, we sort of became aware, not entirely on purpose, but it wasn't really accidental either.
And it's hard to know exactly because some of these frontier labs are not entirely forthcoming with their research.
But we realized that the content that we can create with large language models could actually quite well include software code.
And from software code, we sort of went on to chain of reasoning and then tool use and now we have agents.
So it's not just now content that is a story or written pros or anything.
It's content that actually ends up itself being executable.
So we've gone all the way from intent now to actual execution of code and we can chain these systems together to basically at the point now do almost anything that humans can do on a computer.
So we've got full computer use now.
varying levels of success and massive amounts of supply chain complexity creeps in when you start thinking about this because in traditional security vulnerabilities,
the sort of basis of them all in many cases at least is the ability to influence the control plane from the data plane.
When that separation breaks down,
that gives people who have access to the data plane access to the control plane and then they can change what a piece of software does to make it actually do things that are different from the intent.
In this new model, we effectively merge the control plane and the data plane entirely,
which means protecting the control plane from the data plane becomes much more complex both in the supply chain and during execution.
I may know what you mean, but could you explain what you do mean when you say merging the control plane with the data plane in this new model?
Yeah, absolutely.
So the control plane in software, it's what tells the software what to do.
So it's the instructions that the CPU executes or it's the interpreted language that the interpreter executes.
It's the actual instructions.
In AI, the control plane is the data plane.
It's because the input to the model effectively controls what the output is going to be.
So when that output is used in ways to actually control other things, when it's used to generate code,
that input is both the data and the control because it's saying what's the next token should be, what should this look like, you're giving it intent rather than instructions.
And when that's the weights inside the model that determine what that output is going to look like have as much influence on that or if not more even really than the prompt that you're giving it.
So the data you're feeding into it and the data that it's been trained on affect what comes out of there.
And then when we start introducing things like tool calling and retrieval augmented generation where data is actually added from external sources at runtime.
These external sources then also effectively go into that merged control and data plane where the content in them if not handled extremely carefully can influence what that output looks like.
Let's talk a little bit about the topology of the supply chain.
One type of supply chain is you have code in GitHub.
You push it out maybe compile package it up and deploy it onto some servers on the cloud or it's a hosted application.
there's something like that for AI, but we're also running AIs on everybody's phone, their computers.
What are the different types of supply chains and what are the stops along the way?
So, almost all of them start with pre-training, which is there's got to be a model created at some point for any of this.
And so, for a model to be created, there has to be data.
So pre-training is when we're collecting data that can be used to actually train the model.
So it's run through the training process and it's used to set the weights through that training process.
It's incredibly complicated maths there that I cannot explain.
And so at that stage there's really where does that data come from is the big question.
So there's data that could be your own data that you collect yourself.
It could be data from inside your company.
And when you do that, you've really got to worry about like first of all formatting that data so it's usable, but also what's in that data.
Like if you're using confidential data from inside your company, there's a high risk that that data could leak through a model because we don't really have complete deterministic control over what the model does.
And so that needs to be sanitized or run through some privacy preserving process.
The more common case though, and this is where the real supply chain in models that most of us are using day-to-day begins, is with these predetermined data sets made available by third parties.
There's some proprietary ones.
There's some very large public ones.
There's things like common crawl which is basically a collection of almost all the data from the internet which is often the basis of other data sets where
common crawl is taken and itself is sanitized and put into smaller data sets that are actually more useful for training.
Hugging face has a huge repository of data sets on there that can be used for training.
They also have a library, I think it's a Python library, might be available in other languages called data sets which allows you to bring data sets in from hugging face.
I think it lets you do that entirely automatically just by name.
I don't believe there's any verification in there.
So that's a interesting step there that you need to handle outside of that.
So the next step after that is the training itself and that is when the model is actually created.
Now after that there's fine-tuning and alignment which is taking the trained model and trying to get it to behave in a certain way.
So with alignment we're really talking about alignment to like human values or like don't be awful.
There might be some pretty terrible things in some of these training sets.
You can make every effort to remove them beforehand, but the chance of bias creeping in unintentionally is extremely high.
And so during that alignment process, you can make efforts to fine-tune the model to show it what good structured output looks like and it not including certain topics and things like that.
A lot of people will start with a base model and then we'll fine-tune it themselves.
So there's models that are distributed that are only very lightly fine-tuned and the expectation is that you then fine-tune that model yourself.
There's obviously models that are distributed that are entirely ready to use in chat bots or there's a bunch of training sets out there that let you do chain of reasoning and
things like that where the model comes already trained with that and so you can use it.
There's libraries and there's structured languages that match those training sets and so the models already for lack of better word talks in that format that you want.
The next sort of stage after that I guess is the deployment of the model.
So that's then taking those models.
There's all kinds of public model registries out there.
Hugging face again is probably the biggest one.
There's commercial entities running their own model registries.
There's companies running them inside the company.
I believe Red Hat actually has a repository on hugging face of validated models and then it's deploying those models onto your infrastructure.
Some sort of inference server is usually the standard way.
They could also be like you mentioned deployed on edge devices depending on the size of the model and so on.
I missed a entire step there.
There's quantization and compression and preparing the model as well actually for deployment which so quantization is probably the most common thing that we see happening there.
It's basically some of these models are huge and so one way to get them small in fact they're all huge the L in large language model which literally standing the first L large.
But one of the ways to get them smaller is to quantize them,
which if you're familiar with quantization in any other domain like in musical theory or something where notes are snapped to a grid, it's a similar concept with the models.
So the weights are usually represented as like 32-bit floatingoint integers and so that precision can be reduced.
So there's mathematical methods to take that 32-bit number and make it say a 16- bit number or even a four or 8 bit number.
And when you do that, obviously you do lose some performance of the model.
But we're getting better and better at actually measuring that performance and keeping that performance loss down to a minimum.
But so that's a really effective way to get the model size smaller.
And the smaller the model, then the less memory effectively that you need to run that model for inference.
So if you've got a lot of processing power, a lot of RAM on GPUs, you can run much larger models.
If you don't, if you're using it on a laptop or even a mobile phone, then you want a much simpler, smaller model.
And then there's actually deploying the models as well.
So that might be pre-eploying it in the case of like a handset device or something like that.
That might be spinning models up at runtime in Kubernetes clusters and that kind of thing that goes through your traditional admission control and that kind of thing. Then it's running.
We are familiar with the reasons that attackers go after the supply chain in existing or conventional software.
Maybe trying to gain access to a system, egress data, steal something.
In the case of AI supply chain attacks, what's in it for the attacker?
So, that's a great question and there's a few different motivations.
So the most common motivation, the one that we've actually seen in the wild already multiple times, is actually very similar to your traditional software supply chain attack.
It's just trying to gain access to people's systems.
Some of the training infrastructure is incredibly large and powerful.
So getting access to people's training infrastructure gives you access to all of their GPUs.
It can also get access to their private data and that kind of thing.
The software itself used for model training has rapidly become a more important source of vulnerabilities over the last few years as attackers have realized this.
So the first angle of attack, well I'll call it the first is obviously there's no real order.
It's up to the attackers what they want to do.
But that traditional attack looks to exploit vulnerabilities in that training software stack itself.
And so if they're able to compromise those data training sets or if you're getting data training sets from the internet with no verification or
understanding of where they've come from or anything like that, they can be entirely malicious.
Some of these data sets are actually executable code like they're actually come as like Python pickle objects or other formats that
require serialization that while you expect it to be loading inmemory objects for your training data, you can just embed Python methods or anything like that in there and they'll just execute.
So that's very easy for attackers to put back doors in that.
Sometimes that's expected.
It's highly documented that that can be the case and that you should never load untrusted data into some of these pieces of software.
In other cases, they've actually made efforts to mitigate that and then people have found bugs in that mitigation and those have been exploited as well.
There was a really interesting paper, I think it was only late last year, which is about 200 years in AI time, but just a few months in human time,
from the CSRO Australia, a bunch of researchers there actually started cataloging some of the security vulnerabilities that
the internet had seen in some of the more popular machine learning frameworks and like how the rise of them had just exponentially gone up,
the amount of reported vulnerabilities and the types of vulnerabilities that people were seeing there,
which was I mean again, it's what You would expect as software gets more popular and it hasn't traditionally been written to consider some of these adversarial attacks against it, you'll rapidly will see those attacks go up.
And we've also seen that in the wild multiple times there's been compromised data sets uploaded to Hugging Face where they've just basically been malware.
They've embedded Python code that was just straight up malware.
There was a really large public campaign, I think it was called Shadow Ray and then Shadow Ray 2.0.
The original Shadow Ray campaign, I think, was quite small, but basically they're looking to exploit these kind of vulnerabilities to install crypto miners,
which you can imagine some of this training infrastructure is pretty attractive for running crypto miners on.
You can get yourself some Bitcoin from that.
And then the Shadow Ray 2.0 was essentially the same thing, but by then it was entirely commoditized.
So now we've actually seen this in like the public exploit and bot kits and stuff out there so that anyone can pick these up and off the shelf go and make your own version of it to try and steal people's GPU cycles.
So the more interesting one though and the much harder to detect and understand because we're still in the era of emergent properties coming from AI models.
They're surprising us.
There's active research into understanding them and explainability and there's new things being discovered about them that are not properties that we designed them to have but it turns out they're there.
And so with that in mind, the more interesting attack is influencing the way that the model will actually work based on the data.
So, it's largely known as data poisoning, but there's actually a lot more nuance to it than just simply putting in like bad data, which absolutely does happen.
Like we've seen things like I forget the name of it,
but there's some researchers and they figured out how to like just make tiny changes to images for instance that when AI models either process them or if you trained on them, it did something completely different to what you'd think the image would actually do.
So like if it was labeled by a human to start with, if it's like labeled as a cat, but the model if it's trained on it now, it'll start like saying all laptops are cats and that kind of thing.
I think there was some people that actually used that attack in the wild against self-driving cars. I say in the wild, it wasn't actually used maliciously.
It was just done to prove a point, but I think they were able to make self-driving cars like swerve off a road by putting a specific bumper sticker on another car or something like that.
But I think that really paints the potential danger of these kind of attacks, especially with them being so difficult to detect when these AI systems are used in such safety critical ways.
And we really don't know exactly how they're going to behave.
And the other one that's really interesting there that's also now old in AI years but
new in human years from I think it was also just late last year was attacking the quantization phase where people were able to have a base model.
So one of the ways of sort of detecting what the models do is known as evaluations.
So the safety and security evaluations which is essentially running the model a lot of times with predetermined taxonomy of like inputs and
observing what the outputs are ranking them looking is it saying did I ask it to write code and it actually gave me like this essay on I don't know something horrible instead or it's not that
simple there's obviously more to it than that but that kind of thing they were able to produce a model that it passed all those safety evaluations and like it appeared in all intents and
purposes to be quite functional and safe and everything.
However, when quantized, it actually turns out that then the malicious payload that was in the training data could be triggered.
And so they could distribute this model and it was appeared to be fine.
You could put all the safety evaluations on there, sign them and everything looks great.
Someone else takes it, quantizes it to put it on their smaller device and runs it and now it's vulnerable to the attack.
And so that wasn't even known that that was possible till recently.
And I suspect there's lots of other fun surprises like that that we still don't know about remaining to happen.
There's probably going to be ways to do that both through the mathematical properties like that one and bugs in the software itself as well where
carefully curated and arranged training data with something incredibly subtle in it actually exploits a bug that causes the model to behave differently after it's trained in a way that's not entirely detectable yet today.
which should get everyone a warm fuzzy feeling given the amount of places that these models are being deployed where safety is critical and security is critical.
So I think we are entering an era now where we're going to see or we've already seen it in the last few months.
We're going to start seeing more and more attacks against the models themselves exploiting these kind of properties which will be interesting to see how we actually deal with all of those.
The IT e computer society is now accepting candidates for the new software professional certification.
Whether you're leveling up or ready to lead teams, this certification validates your expertise, backed by the industry's most trusted professional organization in computing.
Visit computer.org/certification to sign up today.
Some of the attacks are easier for me to understand than others.
If I could get a model to run my Bitcoin miner on somebody's GPU, I understand why someone would want to do that or I can get my malicious payload to execute.
It's less clear to me if I could get a model to say that a cat is a laptop or to say something that's wrong or to get a car to drive off the road.
Do we have real world examples of why an attacker would be interested in doing that type of attack?
Would that be industrial espionage or do we know?
That's a great question.
It's difficult to assume the motives of attackers,
but I think nation states it's heavily going to be on espionage and influence campaigns,
especially when models are used for decision-m or for critical purposes or in defense purposes.
The ability for an adversary to be able to influence the behavior of a model that they know is being used in offense or
defense in a military operation against them. like that's incredibly valuable.
So while I have no proof that that is happening, I think common sense we would have to think that it does.
There's also an interesting one where we have seen in real life was with the deepseek models which
I think it was crowdstrike did a bunch of testing on the deepseeek models with code generation and deepseek was surprisingly good at code generation.
I think it was one of the first openw weight models that was sort of capability level of the Frontier models at the time.
What they discovered though is that when it was given certain prompts that were what's the nice way to say this?
Things that the CCP would not like.
So like you're writing software for I should have grabbed their exact prompts.
I can't remember what they were but it was something like this software is to do this thing ABC.
It writes good code.
They say this software is to do ABC for this group that supports Tibet and then it suddenly writes code with like terrible software vulnerabilities and things in it.
Now they stop short of putting this attribution down to anyone doing this on purpose or a reason for it.
But you could connect the dots and say if that's not there on purpose, if that's entirely emergent misalignment,
which it can be like if a model is trained on a data set that's like very heavy politically this direction and you talk politically that direction,
it's actually been discovered that models will behave worse because it's aligned this way.
So all the things it's meant to do, when you start pushing it the other way, it'll do all of them badly, which it's an interesting property of LLMs.
But obviously a more cynical person could look at that and say, "Well, if that's not on purpose, that's a great thing to do on purpose."
Because if you've got a model that you know is going to be used for code generation and someone that you want to be vulnerable to attack from yourself,
that's a really cheap way to suddenly get access to their infrastructure for all kinds of espionage purposes and really brings into view some of the difficulties that
we are going to see as we are using these models more and more for code generation and the need to really check that
code that they generate for things like this both in advance of deploying the model and as it's generating This is making me think of a question.
I interact with LLMs often where I get a response like this makes no sense.
If I was done with conventional software, I might conclude with a similar degree of misbehavior that it's a bug.
But LLMs, as you have said, have all kinds of emergence properties and are probabilistic.
If the weights are attacked, you have a supply chain attack on the model weights, can those be reliably detected or can you differentiate that from simply that's one of those weird things about LLMs.
So detecting the intent is really really hard.
If there is work there where that has been done, I'm not aware of it.
I suspect there is active research there, but I've not seen anything that's made me like take notice and go, "Oh, that's really important."
But certainly there is ways to detect that it is happening which is those evaluations the emails that I was talking about before.
But they of course do not show intent.
They just show that when prompted this way it produces this output.
But they can be run at different stages.
They can be run to simulate you know how you're actually going to use the model yourself.
There's also big libraries like METR, Meta, I think that is how you say it,
where they do very large scale evaluations and then publish all the results and they do the same evaluations across a bunch of different models.
Obviously, you know, there's an element of trust there where you've got to actually trust their results, which is not the same as doing it yourself,
but doing it yourself can obviously be costly and it's can be outside of the realms of capabilities of smaller organizations.
As far as I'm aware, there's not a great way to detect it being done on purpose unless you're taking an existing data set and altering it.
So, this brings us into what some of the protections are here, I guess, right?
Like, so that is a great point to transition to talking about AI supply chain security, which is our ostensible title. So, I would like to set that up.
And now what are some of the main areas or main components of AI software supply chain security?
Yep. So we've got to go through those steps again, I guess.
So with the pre-training data, it's being able to verify the data.
So it's knowing well and as I mentioned when it's your own data and sanitization of the data so removing private or
copyrighted material from it and being able to verify it though that's the important thing like ensuring that it comes from the where it says it comes from the pedigree and
providence just as we have in regular software is all there and intact and that it hasn't been tampered with on disk or in storage or where you're getting it from.
And so that's where the traditional methods of signing and stuff come in there.
Now there's a bunch of nuance to those in here because you're signing very different things and there's different parts of the process to capture.
But there's ongoing work there.
There's in OpenSSF and in SIG store and I think there's even a machine learning SSA adaptation attempt underway now at the moment but they all sort of have the same thing in common and
they overlap with each other and work together.
But that is to cryptographic verification that that data set is not being tampered with and that it is from who it says it is and you can actually verify that.
So then after training when you've actually produced a model again there's model signing.
It's very similar to signing data sets.
In fact there's some complications to model signing.
There's the the opens SSF model signing standard which uses into I believe internally.
It doesn't sign the model itself.
It assigns the inoto at a stations which includes things like its training data and additional meta metadata.
It can also include like definitions of the hardware and so on.
But it's got a major drawback when it comes to this stuff.
So while it does verify that none of that has been tampered with, you still can't actually show that that training data was what was used to train that model.
Like you're just you're still just trusting it that it hasn't been changed. you.
It also provides no guarantee that that model will behave in any way whatsoever.
It's certainly better than nothing.
It's very important to do because it ensures it hasn't been tampered with, but it doesn't provide any real guarantees about the model's behavior or that that model is genuinely derived from that training set that you've signed there with it.
That would be in contrast to repeatable build where I could compile some source code and get the same executable as the CD system.
Exactly. Right.
And even even if you don't have reproducible builds,
you can reverse engineer a binary and you can make not mathematically provable that it is from that exact source code, but you can very much see that very close to functionally equivalent.
You know, it's it's quite hard to hide a backdoor from a very skilled reverse engineer who can take your binary apart and compare it to the source code.
Whereas in a model, that's actually almost trivial to hide.
So, and again, there may be research there that I'm unaware of.
This space moves incredibly fast and it's very important topic to tackle, but I haven't seen anything again that makes me go, well, that's the solution.
That's definitely going to work because it sort of it relies on being able to solve unsolved computer science problems.
When our solutions get to a point where they're now relying on something that possibly can't be solved, that's I think everyone that's worked in software engineering for any amount of time realizes that's pretty much a dead end.
All but you know, the most prestigious academic researchers like in general workplace, we just go, "Okay, well, I'm not going to just solve that on the weekend.
I'll just quickly solve the Turing halting problem and then we'll be fine." That's not a thing that happens.
There is some interesting ways around it with some of the open- source models with entirely open training data as well. There's the Allen AI Institute AI.
I I should really remember the acronym but they developed the Almo model O L M O and
they've developed a system where they publish the training data along with the model but they also build this big index of the training data that's searchable as well.
And what they've done is published this thing where you give an input to the model.
it gives you an output and then you can take that output and look up the index and see where in the training data there's things that match what it said that it probably created them from.
Now, it's not actually deterministic.
It doesn't prove that that's what happened.
But what they've then done is when the model has produced bad output is gone and removed where it looks like it came from from the training data retrained and seen that it no longer creates that.
So again, it's not complete proof.
It's kind of a sidestep shortcut around it, but it's definitely an interesting technique.
Of course, that only works for labs that are willing to publish those indexes of all their training data and all their training data and a tool to do that,
which again, as we've seen, I think they're the only ones who've been willing to do that.
A lot of even the models that score high on the Stanford modeless open index.
I forget what it's called, but Stanford University publishes a list of models and how open they are.
Even the models that score highly on that that use mostly public training sets and document what they do, none of them are anywhere near that open.
In that last discussion, you dropped the term at a station which I have on my notes as something I wanted to ask you about.
Yes. Yeah, that's right.
So, what's done there is the process will attest to that.
So, it will say I have done this and then it'll sign it.
So you've got proof that they claimed that they did that and they know themselves that they did that and that they've signed the real proof or anything, but you are still essentially trusting them.
So they're saying, "Yes, this is definitely done." You're verifying the signature.
You can hold them accountable to that, but it depends entirely on who that party is.
If that party is just some random person on the internet using a pseudonym, they could attest that they've done all kinds of things, sign that at test station, and all the data going into it could be fake.
that signature will still be valid, but it's just not worth anything.
So, it's tying identity to that trust.
So, that identity itself has to have some meaning for you to be able to trust that.
If it's your own infrastructure and you're actually doing what do you call it like when you do a hardware and boot verification of the whole stack and you include all of that
in your outer station, that's very trustable for you yourself.
There's obviously still attacks that can happen there.
There can be bugs in the software.
someone could have influenced something in memory and so on.
But generally, that's a very strong trustable attestation.
And if you then publish that and you're a very well-known public entity such as a business with a lot of customers, there's probably even legal liability and things in there where if you're attesting to lies, you can be held legally responsible for that.
Now, I'm not a lawyer.
I don't know exactly how that works, but there's levels of trustworthiness there.
But it does all come back to trust.
Even without any legal constraints, the greater amount of reputation you have, the more impactful it would be if you were found to have said something that was not true.
Exactly.
And there's transparency matters here as well, right?
Like the amount of transparency that you allow into your systems can help increase that trust as well.
You can make it very hard for you to lie.
You can't make it impossible, but you can make it hard.
Not just in terms of reputational damage that happens, but the ability to be found out can be highly increased.
If you're using public training sets and you also publish them all and the hashes of them and you attest to using those and someone is able to duplicate your process and get very very similar results, that's good.
Like that makes you more trustworthy.
If someone if you give all that information out and someone duplicates your process and gets entirely different results like it just makes no sense whatsoever how their results could be so different.
You know, transparency then is going to make it it harder for you to lie within this area of addistation.
Is there anything like either standards, document standards, bodies,
general agreement on what type of things should be attested or any other consensus across the industry about what should be contained?
Consensus would be a stretch, but there's beginning of consensus.
So going all the way back to the pre-training data sets stage, there's actually a document format.
There was a paper released on calling it data sheets which is it includes the origin, the composition,
the collecting methodology, the labeling process and the known biases in a data set.
There's a derived standard called data cards which I think came from Google which is basically the same thing but
it's an attempt to standardize the format a little bit as well rather than just what it should cover. Not entirely standardized yet.
I have a strong feeling that it needs to be standardized.
I would love for some a standard like that to go to an open- source body and for people to agree on the exact machine readable format for that and you know a way for people to add more things that
should be attested to in that format and so on and you know how standards bodies normally work.
We also have model cards.
It again there's a paper from Google.
I think we're the originators of the model card standard.
Again, it's a loose standard.
It's not an official standard.
There is no set actual standard, but that covers things like the the model architecture itself.
So model architecture is like the layer organization, the routing, how information travels between those layers, the actual mathematical mechanism that a neuron uses to determine an output.
And then it's like whether it's a transformer or a diffusion model, other types of neural networks.
And sometimes while that's always in the model card, sometimes that architecture is in the model itself.
Sometimes that's actually outsourced to the frameworks.
So the model can be loaded in a given architecture or the model can be run and there's executable code in the model that loads the entire architecture.
So there's obviously some very common architectures where like that it's agreed upon what they are but there can be subtle differences between the different frameworks in the implementation which
again another fun thing that can actually influence model behavior.
So there's also in the model card there's the intended use case.
So it's this model can be used as a general chatbot.
It should not be used for this thing.
You should absolutely not use it for safety critical things or you know don't use it if you're a lawyer.
There probably is some case law and things in here that it was trained on, but if you take it to court, you're probably going to get disbarred because it'll just make things up.
Some of them will put very specific out of scope uses in there as well, such as that example.
I think probably to prevent legal liability on themselves, but also just to discourage terrible uses of the model.
Model card will also then often reference those data cards.
So the data sets used in it if they have data cards that exist the model card can then point back to them say we use this data set here as its data card and so on.
Then we have system cards which are is probably seeing a theme here with the card naming.
System cards is sort of the next layer up and this is where you look at the entire AI system as deployed.
So that includes things like the guard rails, the actual software architecture.
Now, something that Red Hat has actually been pushing is to include like a list of weaknesses in there that have have have been fixed in any of those layers as well,
so that there's a way to track those and that can be used for actual verification of the whole system once it's running.
So, make sure what you've got running in production actually matches the description of what you expect it to be for the whole system.
So, not just the model, but the guardrails, the software architecture, all of the API points and so on. Make sure it's all there.
sort of coexisting with these and some overlap is the MLB bomb AI bomb as well which
are very similar to the software bill of materials that'll generally include the model weights themselves hashes of the actual model weights and frameworks that we use for training usually a hash or
some something like that and again these all have the same problems in some cases with those things in there you're just trusting that that's the truth you know when
you're doing it yourself and you're using it for monitoring your own deployments. That's great.
When you're providing these for third parties, you can sign them.
Essentially, you are attesting that these things are true, but it's very hard to prove in some cases. Some of them are easy.
Some of those things are entirely deterministic, others not so much.
I have in my notes model signing and provenence.
We did discuss signing a couple of times.
Is there anything particularly about model signing we haven't covered?
I think we sort of covered it all already.
I guess there's the stages of where you put the verification in your pipeline is important as well.
And whether you resign models yourself if you modify them in any way.
So if you're hosting an internal model registry, you want to be verifying if you're bringing models in from outside, you definitely want to be verifying those before you put them in your registry.
But if you're then deploying those models, which you probably are if well you're hosting an internal model registry,
you've got the question of do I resign them because do I want to just keep adding these other people's keys to what I trust and can be deployed?
Do I want a key that's associated with my registry and so on.
There's also are we doing fine-tuning of these models like do we put a base model here sign the base model with a key that can't be deployed and
there's a validation fine-tuning pipeline process where the input for that has to come from the registry but then the output of that
actually gets signed with your own key and so on and that proves to you that you've done all those things that you said because it's gone through your pipeline and
those can then be deployed I also have some notes about workload identity is that
out to enable that you can be ensured you are talking to the model that you think you're talking to essentially yes so
workload identity gets really complicated with AI so there's the simple view and that is when we're using some sort of workload identity tool spiffy and
spire being probably the the standard at the moment certainly in the cloud native world is that we add that model add a stationation to that which I should have just covered then when
you asked but I completely forgot so as well as just verifying the software stack, you're verifying the model.
And so part of that identity is that the model is the model that that you've allowed that you've authorized on your network.
And then when that model does things like tool use or anything that it needs a token for to access other parts of your infrastructure, it's validated that that is the correct model.
There's something that this doesn't take into account though and this is the intent of the user and the potential for indirect prompt injection as well.
So the intent of the user actually matters in this case.
So if you're going to give models access to internal infrastructure or other services, those services usually contain something valuable or do something.
A really simple example is say Jira software development companies Jira very commonly used for bug tracking all kinds of information about how projects are meant to run and that kind of thing.
You could see lots of use cases where a model needs to interact with Jira through a tool.
Now does that workload get access to update tickets if someone has only asked it for information from a ticket rather than to actually update a ticket?
And how do you know which identity it gets?
Which token it gets like the token with access to write to Jira or just the token that gives it read access to Jira.
Now the really easy solution is to just have a generic system identity that you give it it has full access to Jira.
But if a user has only asked it for information from a Jira and
the Jira that it's looking at contains an indirect prompt injection that actually tells it now go and update this other one with and copy all this data to it and
you know leak information out to someone entirely different. That's probably not ideal.
You do not want that to happen.
So you've got to have some way of mapping that intent to the identity as well.
So, this [clears throat] is what I was alluding to at the start with the supply chain now becoming incredibly complex because both the data that it's reading and
the users prompt have now essentially entered into your control plane and formed part of your supply chain as to what that model is actually executing what those tools are actually doing.
And this is not entirely solved either.
There's attempts to solve this and they're getting better and better.
There's attempts to separate the control plane and the data plane.
There's some technology where they use dual models.
So there's one model that's entirely isolated that determines deterministic output where it's like heavily templated and then the tool use is only in in the template.
And so then the model that actually has access to the tools, you know, the prompt injection will happen at the wrong spot.
There's also lots of isolation technology for the agents and tool use as well where there's fine grained policy where
you can actually you can have some basic intent sort of mapped out and there's you know predetermined policies that you can apply so
it actually gets an entirely different identity to if it's doing task A to task B task C and so you like have those short-lived tokens that
with very limited scope on what they can do again can it be defeated probably [laughter] it's a probabilistic process.
It's very hard to get right.
It is definitely better to do something than nothing.
YOLO mode I think they're calling it now with aic workflows where you just give it access to everything which I have to admit on my personal laptop.
It's great fun to do that.
Just put it in a VM or even give it access to the whole laptop and just give it access to everything.
Let it run as yourself.
the utility there is amazing but
you know in the enterprise use case the risk versus the utility there you
know it starts tipping the other direction pretty quickly as well so I think that's a really hot area of security to watch how that
problem actually gets dealt with at scale getting close to the end G are there any findings researched or
otherwise you're aware of for attacks that have been discovered but have not been seen in the wild that you find particularly noteworthy?
Yes.
So, for stuff that's not seen in the wild, but I suspect is actually happening in security.
I think there's actually a lot of this in general.
It always makes me think of the the survivor bias explanation that um I think we've probably all seen with the airplane and
the holes in it and we put the armor where the holes were and then someone says we should put the armor where the holes aren't because those the airplanes that are shot down.
I think security in general, we suffer from this a little bit where we tend to obsess over the attacks that we caught and don't think enough about the attacks that we got through.
But from an attacker's point of view, they want to be not caught.
The the most successful attacks is not one that we caught like, you know, 80% of the way through and it's done some damage. Now we've stopped it and we've identified the attacker.
It's the one that goes completely undetected.
So I suspect there is research out there. Well, there's definitely research out there.
it's getting published all the time on how to influence the models in the most subtle way possible.
So that you know data that when it's used for training prompts that
can be hidden very very subtly especially over like a large period of time or like across multiple systems where the influence that it has on the model is subtle for the individual but
then at scale it happens over time.
That really scares me a little bit to think that that is happening.
But when I think about it, like how would I carry that attack out?
I don't know that it would be detected yet if it was happening or whether we've really even seen the consequences of it.
Like if you think of the amount of companies that are using AI for decision-m and in important processes and
instead of thinking of the influence on you know I do A B happens but
start thinking like what if I can influence all of these companies at once in a very very subtle way to get a slow action to occur 6 months down the track because they're all just doing small unnoticeable things.
That's a very attractive attack for nation states, huge organized crime networks and so on.
If I worked for one of those, and I don't obviously I work for [laughter] Red Hat, we're very much on the other side of preventing this, not enabling it.
But if I did, that's certainly an area that I would be very interested in what that looks like in practice, which leads me to believe it's probably happening, and we just don't know yet.
Karth, winding down, would you like to point listeners anywhere on the internet where they could find you?
Red Hat.com.
I don't really have a lot going on outside of there.
I am a member of the COSI, the Coalition for Secure AI.
They've got some great resources there.
Technically, I'm on Twitter and those kind of things, but be honest, I really don't use social media anymore since it's kind of turned into a little bit of a cesspool.
Thank you so much for speaking to Software Engineering Radio, Arth. It's been a pleasure.
You too. Thank you for having me.
For Software Engineering Radio, this has been Robert Blumen.
Thank you for listening.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by it e software magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
[music] To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for listening.